tagline for my company [music] is
humanizing AI for care. We've talked
about how healthcare needs to be
emotionally ready before it can be
technologically ready. [music]
Help people feel safe, seen, and
empowered as that change happens.
latchment on something which is already
there and bend on that
>> and hundreds of thousands of dollars on
the data that powers the technology.
>> The goal is to increase access [music]
to healthcare. In this instance, it's
that that sort of awareness,
discernment, judgment experience,
[music]
right? As I always say, we have lived AI
has [music] not human AI co-pilot sort
of partnership and how do you engage in
that partnership. [music]
>> Today on the signal room, we're talking
about what it really takes to scale care
responsibly, not by replacing people,
but by amplifying them. My guest today
is Dr. Mark Gendreau. He has spent his
career at the intersection where urgency
meets innovation. He's an emergency
medicine physician and a senior
healthcare executive who's led teams
through the most complex challenges in
modern care delivery. As a physician
leader has championed datadriven
decision-making, operational readiness,
and a culture of safety that keeps the
human connection at the heart of every
interaction. In this conversation, we'll
explore how AI is beginning to
collaborate with clinicians, where trust
fits into that equation, and what it
means to build systems to help people,
not just process patients. Dr. Jenro,
you spent your career on the front lines
of emergency medicine and being a chief
medical officer. When you hear the
phrase scaling care with AI, what does
that mean in a real hospital setting?
>> Yeah, what it means is that the goal is
to increase access to health care. You
know, we are having greater needs in
terms of the workforce and health care.
We have aging physician workforce,
nursing, and we're having less and less
people entering into health care. So we
need to you know what to me as you said
at the beginning it's more of amplifying
the workforce that we have so that we
can reach more patients and improve the
quality and safety of health care.
Yeah there's just there's a whole
scarcity I think is the word I would use
for a lot of clinical roles and in
especially in the nursing area. I can
see why it's such a focus that you have
to try to use these tools to optimize
the the workflows so that people are
freed up to do the things that they
actually train for, which is helping
people. So, I'm I'm curious. We've
talked a little bit about this and
recently, but I I really would love to
hear and have you share with with some
other listeners where are you seeing
some successes and and how AI is being
used collaboratively with clinicians and
what makes those specific examples
successful in your
>> Yeah. So you know uh three areas really
immediately come to mind to me for in
terms of you know really amplifying
clinicians and transforming their their
uh work life balance as well. So digital
radiology we have AI tools that
basically
read images for example uh CAT scans um
and um you know uh there's various
modules uh that um basically read the
images almost instantaneously.
um they don't interpret, but what they
do is they heads up the radiologist
as to there's something that you should
pay attention to on image 63.
And um some of these algorithms will
actually give you a probability of like
you know if you're doing a CAT scan of
the chest um uh the probability that
that uh could be a pulmonary embolis.
This is incredibly useful. You know, if
you're, you know, particularly in the
nighttime or, you know, there's less and
less radiologists, you know, 12 hours a
day, they're looking at study after
study. There's fatigue that builds in
there. And with that fatigue can be
diagnostic accuracy. So, this really
helps them really kind of focus, you
know, where they should be looking. it
doesn't interpret, you know, that's
still in the hands of the human to
basically discern and judge, you know,
what what is going on and then do the
interpretation. So, I was at a
conference um in the spring and there
was a trauma surgeon in Nevada and they
were they were having issues with
maintaining their trauma designation
with the American College of Surgeons
because they were um having uh they
weren't meeting the guidelines for
having a CAT scan of the head read by a
radiologist so that they could quickly
act upon and they used this AI product
so that it would alert the trauma
surgeon that you know there's an issue
take a look at you know image you know
whatever um and um help them decrease
their time um and get back to trauma
designation. So very very practical,
very useful you know technology that is
really assisting and amplifying the the
physician. Um I would say the second is
in documentation
and so we use ambient
um AI uh platforms to assist um uh
physicians in documentation. This has
been transformative to the primary care
doctors
not only because um it it you know they
that this you know it listens and then
you know when they're done the note has
been generated with about 97%
accuracy as a draft. And this allows the
physician to actually look at the
patient and touch the patient and spend
more time with the patient rather than
having their head buried in the computer
documenting everything that needs to be
documented. And on the other side of
this is we measure something called
pajama time which is we we can see when
physicians are in um the EHR after hours
>> um and we see people who are still
trying to catch up 10 11:00 at night and
um you know this is not sustainable. So,
you know, that is a second example of
the utility of it. We have another we
have an ED that is using an ambient
system that also when you're done with
your note, it gives feedback to the
clinician, you forgot to introduce
yourself. the patient seemed to be a
little bit tense when you were saying
that and your response, you know, you
could have, you know, you could have
approached it this way. So, not only are
you getting that documentation
that the physician or the advanced
practice provider is getting feedback to
be a better clinician on a more human
level. you know, uh, these technologies
are really amplifying the human in
healthcare and not automating them.
>> That's fascinating. I I actually was
speaking with a company yesterday
scheduled for a half hour. I think I
stole another half hour from them cuz I
was excited watching having them walk me
through what they were doing. But it was
exactly what you're describing in terms
of really undergirling and supporting
the the clinical interaction. So with
every staff person that interacts with
the patient, it's actually profiling the
individuals that are interacting with
the patient. It's it's profiling with
the patient and it's detecting much like
you said, detecting if there's tension
or stress involved, not only analyzing
the words, but actually analyzing and
detecting tone in the voice and that the
things that would indicate that there's
stressor involved. Fascinating to me.
had had not heard of anything that was
geared towards wrapping around the
encounter regardless of who the
individual was that was interacting with
the patient. But they're having some
really great success. It's actually
being done by a physician who's got come
out of um Stanford out in California.
Definitely share some of that
information with you, you know, later
later today um just so you can take a
look at what they're doing. It sounds
like something that would be uh right up
your alley. as a as an advocate for, you
know, helping to relieve that the burden
that we've continued to layer on to to
clinicians. You've touched on some some
great examples of where AI is is being
useful. Is there an example that stands
out in your mind where there's a
specific decision where AI added value
or where it didn't and what that taught
you about boundaries between the human
and the machine? Yeah, you know, I
think, you know, just to, you know, like
where has AI sort of not been as
stellar, you know, these we're
essentially, you know, 5 to 10 years
into AI, right? And really into AI over
the last I would say uh 3 four years and
um you know, we see improvement all the
time. But take for example the digital
radiology where these AI algorithms will
basically alert you to something. Um
they still have um issues with them like
they will sometimes um um think
something's going on and it turns out
that you know when the radiologist looks
at it it's like no that's a benign
calcification.
um you know uh that isn't anything that
we need to worry about and and so there
lies you know as I say you the human
brain always keep the human in the loop
with this right healthcare um and other
industries where there's you know high
reliability
you have to have human in the loop every
time um and um you know in this instance
it's that that sort of awareness
discernment judgment experience right as
I always say we have lived AI has not
and it's those reps that you know the
clinician or the radiologist in this
particular example who's read thousands
and thousands and thousands of images
that those reps you know give that
judgment and that insight ite that no
that's not anything that we need to be
worried about that doesn't need to be
reported you know in that fashion that
becomes very important
>> exactly you know I was thinking about a
simple example where you know if you're
my physician and I historically have a a
bit of high blood pressure it's
controlled with medication or whatever
but that any elevation detected by AI
would be flagged and so If no one knows
that this is normal for me and it's it's
time being treated, I mean there there
can be decisions made that aren't
necessary or alerting that could happen.
No, alert fatigue is something that I've
heard quite a lot about over the years.
Um, working in IT departments in
particular, I heard I've heard a lot of
uh feedback that was not necessarily
favorable about the alerts that we were
triggering for like seems like
everything under the sun. So, want to
kind of dig into trust a little bit. I
know we talk a lot about you know do we
trust AI? I know we've we've discussed
this and more recently I've been hearing
a lot more conversation about the trust
in human relationships with technology
moving so fast we we know that trust
still is built slowly and deliberately
what helps clinicians trust AI insights
enough to act on them?
>> Great question. So you know you think
about what is trust right and um Stephen
Covey wrote a book on trust actually I
believe two books on uh trust and he
defined trust as trust is an equation
that has credibility plus judgment plus
safety. He called that intimacy but he
was meaning more like psychological
safety
>> right
>> and divided by self-orientation
or you know you know uh the you know is
what is this being used for is this
being used for good or is this being
used for bad so kind of the ethics uh
component um of it
>> and so I think that you know we can kind
of you know for AI for um because
healthc care is is you know a field of a
lot of relationships of trust of quality
and safety and so you know it needs to
have those kind of components of trust
of you know uh the capabilities have to
be good the reliability
of it needs to be solid you know we're
not going to trust something that you
know has a reliability you know like you
know half the time there's issues with
its output or what it's actually doing
and you know it's got to be it's got to
contribute to safety and so I think
those are kind of you know the
components of trust and AI adoption I
think when those are met clinicians feel
more comfortable interacting with AI and
you know we've seen This with our
ambient uh uh docu you know hearing
documentation platforms is initially the
clinicians are a little bit reserved on
this they're you know their trust is
very guarded but as they become more
comfortable with that interaction as AI
starts learning about their preferences
and what they like what they don't like
um and when they praying it saying you
know you said this the patient actually
said this that is all that's the
interaction that you need then the trust
comes and people are more word gets out
and people you know adopt it you we we
had a lot of laggers uh with high you
know with our ambient u plat uh AI
platform
and um as soon As more and more of the
early adopters, late adopters, you know,
um, uh, came aboard, we we leveraged
their them to influence the laggers to
come on board and some of those laggers
become the biggest sort of champions of
the technology.
>> That's phenomenal. Yeah. I I I've often
seen things kind of go sideways when the
these type of efforts are viewed as an
IT project. We've, you know, we'll
build, you know, I don't mean this that
everyone does this, but I know
historically there's been a lot of times
where solutions were developed and and
just imposed and, you know, they, you
know, people have spoken to in your
profession have looked at me and giving
me an eye roll like you did it to me
again. Why are you wasting my time? This
does not solve a problem I actually
have. But there are some you could solve
if you'd like to listen. I love how
you're approaching it. I'm sure that
your colleagues are grateful that that
you're kind of on on the tip of the
spear in leading through this because it
is a a bit of a frightening exercise
when you've got all these things coming
at you, this pressure to use it and you
know this this explosive growth in
volumes of data that you have to process
quickly to to diagnose something or to
to decide how to treat it. We we've only
been layering and layering constantly
whether it's for the purpose of
improving quality. we we they we add
data elements that have to be captured
and then all of a sudden there's
penalties being imposed based on a an
average rather than an individual which
I don't think is a interesting problem
that we're going to have to solve for in
regulatory areas because you know as you
know if you take the averages that we're
we're measuring against you're never
going to find an individual anywhere on
the planet that matches that profile but
yet we decide to penalize or or
incentivize based on that the practice
of medicine and is an involving science
of course. So I don't know how we are
going to get there. But I think we
really have to lean in on the regulatory
side and make sure they understand the
regulatory nature of things historically
has not been based on reality. It's been
based on a static snapshot in time
essentially which is not going to work
with AI. What you're doing in your
building I think is a it's it's really a
culture that that you're developing
there. How do hospitals, how should
hospitals be thinking about creating
that culture where the data and human
judgment reinforce each other instead of
competing because I know there's in some
cases a tension between those things.
>> Yeah, I I think that you know it needs
to come from leadership, right?
Leadership plays a big role in this of
uh of um showing people that you know
getting them involved in this, giving
them agents,
really allowing people to experiment
with it and be creative with it. Um you
know, all that is part of change
management. So
when you're working on these types of
things, there's there's one thing when
you're just trying to kick the tires and
try to get people used to it, but at
some point you got to start figuring out
how do you how do you scale it and what
are the indications that you're going to
be looking at to determine when it's
actually time to scale. So from an
operation standpoint, what are some of
the challenges to to scaling these AI
systems across the health system that
you've encountered? I would say the
biggest obstacle is um threefold. I
think it's interoperability is probably
the biggest one. Um and then governance
is is uh the third and then basically
what what's a good term for it? it. How
are you how your structure with respect
to the you know in in terms of training
the models you know like a a lot of
health systems now are partnering with
you know one of the big AI LLM
uh you know companies and using their
model parking it behind a firewall
and then training it with internal
things, right? So that the so that the
model starts to kind of get an
understanding. They it knows who we are.
It knows what we do and things of that
nature. We're actually being very busy
in our health system with um um and
making sure that it's ready for prime
time uh for the the masses in the health
system. And you know we've been busy
with setting up uh governance
you know what do we push out when do you
know to who and how do we do it and
>> uh aspects of of that and then the
interoperability
is you know is um a big big thing right
because it involves getting the right
APIs
making sure that everything is talking
to each other because if you don't do
that the data um is just not useful to
you. Those are I think the key
components of of of scaling up AI um
health system. This was all pointed out,
by the way, in um 2022
um when the um National
Academy of Medicine put out a a uh
document on uh artificial intelligence,
um you know, with respect to healthc
care. That's a worthwhile read um if you
haven't read it.
>> I appreciate that. there's this human
factor that often times just it doesn't
get the time and attention that it
needs. And one of the most important
things that I've realized that I need to
help message is start with listening and
you know having conversations with with
someone like yourself. This is a really
important uh thing if you're going to
try to develop any kind of solution to
make things better.
You're talking about scaling. What are
some of the signals that that you're
looking for to know when your
organization's ready? This is not just a
technical readiness, but there's the
cultural aspect of it as well.
>> I would say um when kind of like what I
you know what I alluded to is that the
you've got leadership who's involved
right like the beauty of AI is that you
don't need to be techsavvy.
um you need techsavvy people but for the
most part I mean I'm not tech right but
that's the beauty of AI is that AI
really doesn't uh that the lot most
people who do very well in AI seem to be
not techsavvy but people who are
creative are good problem solvers and
then have those core elements of like
human centric leaders ersship that
they've got strong empathy, they're
ethical, they they're you know truh
trust is a building trust is a
non-negotiable
sort of thing with them and I think that
>> you know when you've got leadership who
isn't trying to basically push it to it
to roll out but it's the upper
leadership who is is is basically
you know, like we need to do this and
here is the why and here is the how.
Then I think you know that culture
changes more and more people start using
AI you know for like generative AI um
and um it just becomes a catalyst for
readiness and I think that there's you
know there's multiple layers on how do
you know when your organization is ready
I think it's not just one thing it's
multiple things
>> yeah absolutely it it's it's a lot more
complex than um we would like it to be
for sure. You touched on something else
with the this ethical considerations and
one of the things that's been
challenging my thinking and I I'm not
quite sure if this really requires guard
rails. It may actually require some that
we can we have to figure out. But how
empathetic do we really want the
technology to be? Because there's a risk
now that people trust too quickly and
too easily and that that's a concern.
Where where do you think some of these
lines might be to make sure that we're
keeping medicine focused on on on human
beings and trusting human beings and
we're making sure that empathy doesn't
get lost in the in our rush to to get
efficiencies.
>> Yeah. You know, I mean AI is great at a
lot of different things. pattern
recognition, you know, some, you know,
I'm all for automating repetitive, you
know, um, things that, um, are fairly
routine in terms of patient care. But I
think that if if if you're doing
something that requires emotional
intellig, you know, something that is
going to require uh emotional
intelligence, relationship building, or
shared decision, that ain't AI's
territory. That's the human, right? And
one of my one of favorite um favorite
quotes from Jeff Woods um is you know
you are the leader and don't ever
abdicate your leadership to AI. And so I
would flip that to you are the human
never abdicate your role your humanness
to AI. I think that I was listening to a
podcast recently
um and they were discussing they were
discussing like how as you know as we
become more and more into AI and it
becomes more agentic and things of that
nature we're going to have an AI uh
we're going to have two workforces we're
going to have an AI workforce we're
going to have a human workforce the
important thing that we have to do is
that we need to make sure that we keep
those kind of separate like we don't try
to humanize the AI and start calling it
names and everything because the
technology is going to there's some
technology out there that you can't tell
the difference if you're speaking to a
human or a robot,
>> right? Um and um and so we we have to
make sure that we don't get down that
track too far because um we giving away
um uh our human traits is just not going
to be a good thing.
>> No, it's it's clearly a risk and I think
the dangers that are there because
there's also this trust factor. Um, we
can't we can't be sure that we're going
to get people to really follow the
guidelines on what you should and
shouldn't use these technologies for.
>> Increasingly, people are connecting,
listening to, being influenced by people
who look, think, sound, and behave like
they do, and they're not necessarily
listening. often times that that can be
a real miss if you're trying to run an
organization as a CEO and your your
people aren't trusting you that you're
you're you're going to do things in a in
a way that they don't have to be
terrified of losing their jobs that
there's got to be an awareness that you
got to find ways to message so so that
you know that people are really
understanding and and they can actually
make the decisions to follow it. From a
leadership standpoint,
I think there's a there's a really
significant need to understand better uh
what the experiences are for clinicians.
We haven't gotten too far into the to
the burnout uh kind of conversation, but
we know that there's a fair amount of
that because, you know, you mentioned
documentation being done up until 10
11:00 at night. How should leaders be
thinking about protecting their
clinicians from things like the alert
fatigue or overautomating?
But still, we want to make sure that
we're moving innovation forward.
>> Yeah. You know, I mean, you know, alert
fatigue is big, particularly in the
nursing side of things, right? Because
they're up there um on the floors
continuously and there's alarms going
off everywhere. And I would say that
alert, an alert needs to earn the right
to interrupt a clinician, right? I think
is a good way to think about it moving
forward. And so, and then another
principle is if you're going to add
something, you need to take something
away, right? in terms of and so we have
we have so many techn you know we have
so much technology uh with alarms and
everything that um one of the big things
that um you know we have become
increasingly more concerned about is um
it almost becomes just background noise
that um the people don't even uh hear it
and so um that's why you know it's on
it's on humans and leadership in
healthcare to put together alert com uh
fatigue committees and actually review
what is what sends alerts,
>> right? and what's the what's the value
that it's providing and what's the
impact that it's doing and what you know
uh if it's not adding value and it's
having a negative impact we need to
basically change up that technology that
that fits the whole purpose of of of the
podcast that I've created here there's a
ton of noise and it you know if
everything is triggering an alert
there's really no point anymore cuz
that's all you're going to do is respond
to alerts and that that's just not a
productive way to to use the technology.
I think it's going to be a very
interesting challenge because there just
seems to be so many great ideas coming
coming forward and I'm sure that you're
getting a full inbox
with your emails from people who have
the best things in sliced bread, but
it's only going to solve a fraction of a
problem that you really want to solve.
And that's just not sustainable. But
there's so many of them coming at us all
the time. It's really hard to detect
sometimes where are where is something
where's the one that's got some real
value and can have some real impact.
>> There's a lot of noise out there.
>> There is.
>> And that signal to noise ratio we got we
got somehow make that better.
So if we look forward 5 years from now,
you're speaking of signals, what do you
think will be the single most important
one that you'll be watching that tells
you that this AI and human collaboration
are actually improving care?
>> I would say outcomes um you know that
we're we're seeing better health
outcomes. We're seeing, you know, the
dispar the health disparities gaps um uh
shrink or go away totally.
Um and pajama time goes down to zero. I
think are those are the signals that
would tell me that um we've succeeded.
Well, you you just used a term that I'm
sure I'm not the only one that hasn't
heard this, but please help me
understand what what the pajama time is
really all about. That's probably doctor
code, I imagine.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, that's that's you know so we when
when um when a clinician is documenting
you know 10 11 12:00 at you know at
12:00 in the morning um to catch up on
documentation
that's what we call pajama time I I
might have to borrow that but I'll give
you credit
Dr. Gendreau, if if folks are are uh
interested in reaching out to you to
obviously to to to understand what it is
that you're doing that you're seeing be
bring successful adoption, how do they
reach you?
>> They can best reach me on LinkedIn.
>> Fantastic. And and for for those that
are listening, I'll make sure that you
have all the information you need in the
show notes to to reach out to Dr.
Gendreau. It's been a pleasure to have
you on today. Fascinating conversation.
I'm sure we'll be having more of them in
the future. But thank you so much for
for taking the time. It means a great
deal to me personally. So, thank you for
being here, Dr. Gendra.
>> You bet, Chris. Thank you.
>> Well, that's going to do it for this
episode of the Signal Room. If today's
conversation sparks something in you, an
idea, a challenge, or a question, don't
keep it to yourself. Join the
conversation on LinkedIn or visit us at
signalroompodcast.com.
We're here to amplify the signals that
matter across leadership, ethics, and
innovation in healthcare.